<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fears and jealousies ceas'd, or, An impartial discourse, tending to demonstrate from the folly and ill success of the Romish politicks, that there is no reason to apprehend any danger from popery in a letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>Doolittle, Thomas, 1632?-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12533</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12333582</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12333582</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36317)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 208:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fears and jealousies ceas'd, or, An impartial discourse, tending to demonstrate from the folly and ill success of the Romish politicks, that there is no reason to apprehend any danger from popery in a letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>Doolittle, Thomas, 1632?-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: T.D. [i.e. Thomas Doolittle].</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:59720:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59720:1"/>
            <head>Fears and Jealouſies Ceas'd: Or, an Impartial Diſcourſe, tending to Demonſtrate, from the Folly and ill Succeſs of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, that there is no Reaſon to Apprehend any Danger from Popery. In a Letter to a Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOurs I receiv'd, and to my no ſmall admiration, find that you ſtill continue to ſtuff your Letters with the old Common place Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of <hi>Fears and Jealouſies,</hi> and of the Dangers we are in at preſent; but not content with this, you are pleas'd to give me a moſt Tragical Deſcription of our future condition; How our <hi>Church</hi> is to be deſtroy'd, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſet together by the Ears, whilſt our <hi>Popiſh</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall ſtand by, clap us on the back, ſpit in our mouths, and hearten us on to cut one anothers Throats: Who (as you ſay) when they ſhall be cloy'd with the Sport, will take the Sword out of our Hands, finiſh the Work we have ſo bravely begun, by diſpatching thoſe that remain; or at leaſt, reducing them to ſubmit to that heavy Yoak, which we ſee our Miſerable Brethren of <hi>France</hi> groan under at this day.</p>
            <p>Theſe things ſet off with the advantages of your Popular Air and Stile, ſome Weeks ago, might perhaps have made a deep Impreſſion, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the thick Skulls of your Country Neighbours, but likewiſe in the Minds of thoſe that are more converſant in the World; certain it is, that ſomething of that Nature did ſtartle many, that in all outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſeem'd to be much clearer ſighted than our common Pretenders to Politicks. Nor indeed were they much to be blam'd, who cou'd ſcarce perſwade themſelves that our <hi>Church</hi> was deſign'd to be maintain'd in its Ancient Splendor, when ſuch undue Methods were taken to extinguiſh the moſt eminent Lights within it. What hopes had we of enjoying our former Peace and Tranquillity, when we ſaw every little Canting Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleteer not only ſuffer'd, but encouraged, nay hired, to foment our Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities, to widen our breaches with their ſcurrilous Libels, and by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Forgeries, endeavour to exaſperate the Rabble againſt their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors; whilſt in the mean time our Diſſenting Brethren without, inſtead of joyning with us againſt the Common Enemy, were allur'd with Penſions to purſue their petty Quarrels with all the Rancour imaginable; and our dangerous Aſſenting Brethren tempted with Preferments to betray us from within. Who cou'd imagine that our Government was ſafe, when we ſaw all thoſe Prudent Laws which our Wiſe Anceſtors were a making
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59720:2"/> for above theſe hundred years, ready to be blown away at one blaſt? What Perſon cou'd be ſecure of his Birth-right, or Body Politick of its Rights and Priviledges, conſidering the havock that was lately made in our Corporations and Univerſities? Theſe Conſiderations, I ſay, ſome ſmall time ago, were able, no doubt, to Conjure up again the Old Devil of Fears and Jealouſies, which perhaps, had things remain'd in the ſame Condition, all the Eloquence of our State Orators could never have been able to lay. But now to uſe the Learned Expreſſion of a late Dull Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical Scribler, <hi>Ceſſante Cauſa tollitur Effectum.</hi> His <hi>Majesty</hi> has by one Act render'd the Malice of our Enemies as impotent as their Arguments; he has made all our Fears to vaniſh; he has ſecur'd our Rights, Laws, and Religion; in a word, he has as it were re-eſtabliſh'd the Church of <hi>England.</hi> It is this inſurmountable Bulwark that muſt be firſt undermin'd, before any attempts can be made, with the leaſt ſucceſs, upon our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Government: But whilſt it ſtands firm and unſhaken, as we have now all the Reaſon in the World to believe it ever will, in vain torment we our ſelves with Jealouſies, in vain do the Factious Male-Contents ſuggeſt to us their Chimerical Dangers of Popery, and its inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Concomitants, Tyranny and Slavery: And I don't doubt, but I ſhall be able in the following Diſcourſe, to make it clearly evident, That all Inſinuations of that Nature, are at this time of the Day, altogether as groundleſs, as the ſpreaders thereof ſhew themſelves the moſt ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Men towards his Sacred Majeſty.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe, by the Liberty I have already taken, you will not ſuſpect that I would go about to Banter you with the Shams of an Occurrencer, or endeavour to wheedle you into a deſtructive ſecurity, by the baſe and deteſtable Artifices of the <hi>French</hi> Politicians, who at that very Inſtant of time, when the Revocation of the Edict of <hi>Nantes</hi> was drawing up, gave out ſeveral Declarations, in which they made the moſt ſolemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations that it ſhould be kept inviolable. No, I ſhall diſcover my thoughts to you with the Sincerity of a Proteſtant, and that Freedom of Speech which is the Inborn Right of an <hi>Engliſhman.</hi> I ſhall Impartially weigh, to the beſt of my Capacity, all thoſe Reaſons which make this <hi>Phantom</hi> of Popery appear ſo terrible to us, and don't at all doubt but that I ſhall eaſily make it evident that it is but a vain Shadow, and that we are ſo well ſprinkled with <hi>Holy Water,</hi> that it has no power <hi>to approach to hurt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the firſt place, I ſuppoſe you'll agree with me, that before <hi>Popery</hi> can gain any ground upon us here in <hi>England,</hi> it muſt firſt take poſſeſſion of, and ſtrongly fortifie it ſelf in the Noddles of a great part of the Rabble, it is from hence that the <hi>Booted-Apoſtles</hi> muſt be rais'd, This muſt be the <hi>Seminary</hi> to furniſh us with <hi>Miſſionaries,</hi> to Convert ſuch as have any Brains in their Heads, which as <hi>Dear Joy</hi> ſays very well, muſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59720:2"/> certainly be firſt beaten out, before there be any room for <hi>Popery.</hi> Let us ſee therefore, whether it be ſeazible for our <hi>Romiſh</hi> Friends to gain ſuch a Party amongſt us, as thereby to entertain any hopes of effecting their Deſigns.</p>
            <p>If we conſider the good old <hi>Popery</hi> in its pure Naturals, we ſhall find it to be ſuch a hideous Monſter, as the moſt Ignorant and Stupid amongſt us, will be ſo far from being enamour'd with, that the moſt effectual way to create in them an irreconcileable averſion to it, is to let them but have a view of it. But its <hi>Holy Mother,</hi> the Church, you'll ſay has been a long time a <hi>Tricking</hi> up this ſweet Babe of hers: The <hi>Damm</hi> has been above theſe Hundred and Fifty years a licking her <hi>Cubb</hi> into ſome more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Shape, it is confeſs'd; and inſtead of a ſhapeleſs innocent Lump (I mean in Compariſon of what it is at preſent) has produc'd a moſt <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Beaſt of Prey,</hi> one <hi>Paw</hi> of which, is certainly more terrible to us than its whole <hi>Body</hi> was to our <hi>Forefathers.</hi> Let us caſt our eyes a little upon our Neighbouring Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> where, as it is confeſs'd by all, that above any place in <hi>Europe</hi> the moſt <hi>Refin'd Popery</hi> is eſtabliſh'd; (for as for <hi>Spain,</hi> it does for the moſt part jogg on after the old rate ſtill; and in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> that's an Article of Faith one <hi>Poſt Day,</hi> which is Damnable Hereſie ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.) If we look into <hi>France,</hi> I ſay, and behold with what barbarous cruelty they uſe the poor Proteſtants there, what unheard of Torments they make 'em endure, we ſhall find that <hi>Hanging, Burning,</hi> and <hi>Cutting</hi> of <hi>Throats,</hi> is but <hi>Plain Work,</hi> in compariſon of the more exquiſite Inventions of thoſe Modern <hi>Executioners.</hi> Now if theſe be the Effects of <hi>Refin'd Popery,</hi> I leave you to determine what Stomach People can have to fall in love with our <hi>Super-Refiners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you'll object perhaps, that whatever concerns <hi>France,</hi> is wholly Forreign to us; and that the greateſt part of our Nation is not to be mov'd with any thing but what we our ſelves ſee acted, or at leaſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber done. As to the former part of this objection, I anſwer that the ſame Cauſes muſt neceſſarily produce the ſame Effects; We ſee that our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verters brought over their Doctrine along with them from <hi>France,</hi> a little mended I muſt confeſs according to their poor Abillities: They purſued the ſame Methods to propagate it as the <hi>French</hi> did before they took off the Mask, and had not his Majeſty been Graciouſly pleas'd to ſtop their Proceedings, there is no doubt but that their Endeavours wou'd not have been wanting to imitate to the Life, if not to improve the Original.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond part of the objection, I will ſuppoſe it at preſent to be true; that moſt men here are wholly ignorant of the Affairs of their Brethren abroad: Yet have they learn't from the Actions and Writings of the <hi>Propagators</hi> themſelves, enough to make them for ever deteſt that <hi>Religion,</hi> which ſuggeſts to her Followers ſuch treacherous means, as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59720:3"/> they have uſed to introduce it: To prove which I need only put you in mind of ſome of their brave exploits for which they will never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in <hi>England;</hi> and from hence you may eaſily imagin how mightily they are like to prevail amongſt us.</p>
            <p>You cannot but remember how in his <hi>late Majeſties</hi> Reign, the greateſt part of thoſe Perſons who had diſtinguiſht themſelves for their Loyalty to their <hi>Prince,</hi> and Affection to their <hi>Church,</hi> ſeeing a moſt Powerful Party of the Nation furiouſly enrag'd againſt the whole <hi>Canaille</hi> of theſe Miſcreants, took compaſſion on their ſufferings, and without over-curiouſly examining their Caſe, but judging by themſelves that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for Animals in Human ſhape to be guilty of what they were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd, ſnatch't them out of the fire, tho' they burnt their own hands by the bargain; ſtood in the Gap betwixt them and Death, and abandon'd themſelves to the Fury of the incens'd Multitude, to preſerve theſe Wretches. Now after ſuch ſignal obligations one might reaſonably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſome ſmall ſigns of Gratitude from them to their Protectors; But they that did ſo knew them not; and they that had unwarily Nouriſht them in their Boſoms, ſoon found what a <hi>Generation of Vipers</hi> they had to deal with: Who as ſoon as they were warm fell a <hi>Hiſſing</hi> and <hi>Spitting</hi> their <hi>Venom</hi> at their Benefactors. Surely we might have hop'd for at leaſt that Favour at their hands which the <hi>Cyclops</hi> gave to <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> to be the laſt objects of their outragious Malice: But theſe more <hi>Savage</hi> Monſters of Ingratitude ſcorn'd to follow the ſteps of any in their Villanies, and were reſolv'd to become an Original themſelves never to be imitated.</p>
            <p>But I will yet ſuppoſe that there are many <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> who out of the abundance of their Charity, will abſolve theſe good <hi>Fathers</hi> of what has been hitherto ſaid, and lay all the fault at the door of <hi>Holy Church.</hi> The <hi>C.</hi> of <hi>E.</hi> they'll ſay was the greateſt obſtacle to the Introduction of <hi>Popery,</hi> ſhe therefore muſt be deſtroy'd, let the means to bring it about be never ſo Infamous: Their Religion diſpenſes with all thoſe <hi>petty</hi> toys call'd <hi>Honour, Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Morality,</hi> whenſoever her own advancement is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd. Well, granting theſe to be the Principles they ſuck'd from the Breaſts of their <hi>Holy Mother,</hi> yet a Man would think they might have the <hi>ſenſe</hi> to conceal them from us <hi>Hereticks,</hi> or the Common People at leaſt; the moſt part of which are not ſo very converſant with the <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> as to have their ſtomachs prepar'd to digeſt ſo crude a Doctrine. But if we take a ſhort view of their late Actions, we ſhall find it to be a matter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, whether they have not ſhown themſelves not only to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning part of Mankind, but even to thoſe of the meaneſt Capacity, to be greater <hi>Fools</hi> than <hi>Villains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a bold Aſſertion, I confeſs, eſpecially in a matter where the <hi>Reverend Fathers the Jeſuits</hi> are concern'd: But I'll appeal to any one
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59720:3"/> whether it be poſſible for a more ſtupendious piece of Folly to enter into the thoughts of Man, than that which our <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Politick Miſſionaries</hi> were guilty of, when they had the Confidence to maintain, not in a Corner, but in the Face of the whole World, ſuch <hi>Forgeries,</hi> which there was not a Boy, whoſe Memory ſerv'd him for <hi>five years,</hi> but might diſcover, and at the ſame time give the <hi>Good Fathers</hi> the Lye in their Teeth. Who would bluſh for theſe men, when he ſees in their Writings the Church of <hi>England</hi> accus'd of all the Extravagancies of ſome fiery Diſſenting Zealots in the late Plot time: The Church of <hi>England</hi> men, not excepting the Biſhops themſelves, repreſented as the Contrivers, Promoters, and Managers of the Bill of Excluſion: Nay, and one that had never known any thing of our concerns, would gueſs by their Libels that the whole <hi>Church</hi> had been reſolv'd into a <hi>Camp</hi> in the time of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Invaſion, and that all her Members had ſworn to live and dye with the <hi>Rebel;</hi> when at the ſame time, I need not tell you how notorious it is to all that have ever heard any thing of our late Tranſactions, that it was for the <hi>Heighth</hi> of their Loyalty to their late Soveraign, their Zeal for His preſent Majeſties Service, in oppoſing the <hi>Bill</hi> before, and the quelling of the laſt and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing efforts of his Enemies, ſince his coming to the Crown, that was the great occaſion of all thoſe Heats and Animoſities, which our Common Adverſaries (whoſe preſervation was not the leaſt ingredient towards the enflaming of them) have endeavour'd ſince to make ſo great an advantage of. But ſhall we be angry with theſe Ingenuous men who have thus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented us? By no means; let them alone and have <hi>Rope,</hi> and (as the Proverb ſays) they'll hang themſelves. They can do us no greater Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice than continue to rail at us; the beſt Arguments in the World to make People deteſt and abhor them, are their own elaborate Writings: For can you think it poſſible that any Idiots ſhould be ſo ſenſlleſs as to believe theſe Perſons in the Stories they tell, of ſome Hundreds of years ſtanding, when they find ſo many groſs Impoſtures in reports they make of things that were done, as it were, but Yeſterday?</p>
            <p>I cannot therefore help ſmiling, to ſee you ſo ſerious in bringing forth one of your main Reaſons for your <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>Popery;</hi> and that is forſooth the <hi>profound Politicks,</hi> which the Managers of that Party have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſo famous for. Not many years ago we might perhaps have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended ſomething from them of that Nature, whilſt we are ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic'd in their Favour; by all the Hiſtories of the laſt age, whereby we learn that in thoſe days they never acted any of their more eminent Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, till their Plots were ſo laid that they cou'd ſcarce fail of ſucceſs, and apparent advantages to the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>It was only upon ſuch well grounded Deſigns that they rais'd Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, and Murthered Princes and others in their Perſons and Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59720:4"/> It was for the Advancement of the Catholick Church, that they contriv'd, and carried on the <hi>Holy League</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the 3d, and his Majeſties Grandfather <hi>Henry the 4th,</hi> and to ſecure it, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them both. It was to put this Nation into perpetual Confuſion that they endeavour'd to blow up his <hi>Majeſties</hi> other Grandfather <hi>King James the firſt,</hi> together with the beſt part of the Nobility and Gentry. They Encouraged and aſſiſted the <hi>Scotch</hi> Rebels againſt his Father K. <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>first,</hi> that they might ſet us Hereticks a cutting one anothers Throats: It was to reduce the <hi>Low Countries</hi> to the Obedience of the <hi>Holy See</hi> that the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> was Aſſaſſinated. It was to create an abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the minds of people againſt <hi>Hereſy,</hi> that they Banter'd the Poor Ignorant <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and made them believe that <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> ever ſince the Reformation were ſhap'd like <hi>Dragons;</hi> and reported all about the World that the <hi>Devil</hi> was run away with <hi>Luther</hi> alive.</p>
            <p>But, as there are certain Periods of time for the Riſe and Fall of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arts and Sciences, ſo it is no wonder if we find a ſenſible Decay in the once ſo flourſhing <hi>Politiques</hi> of the <hi>Religious Society;</hi> It is manifeſt to all men what wretched Bunglers our Preſent Aukward Pretenders to them have ſhew'd themſelves. For tho' it cannot be denied that they, Poor Souls, have always diſcover'd a willing mind to imitate the moſt Notorious of their Predeceſſors in their moſt execrable Crimes; nay, and I dare ſay that for them, they are ſo well become Conſcience proof, that as far as the promoting of any Miſchief goes, their weak endeavours ſhall never be wanting to ſurpaſs them if it were poſſible. Yet if one ſhoud enquire how the <hi>Catholick</hi> Cauſe has thriv'd under their hands; he'l ſoon find that inſtead of Effecting any of thoſe Glorious Enterpriſes which their Brave Anceſtors by executing, have render'd their Names deſervedly Infamous, to all ſucceeding Ages; they with all the <hi>Buſtle</hi> and Clutter they have made in the World, have gain'd nothing but the <hi>Odium</hi> of all Mankind; without being guilty of any thing that look'd like a deſign, or at leaſt but ſuch as has been ſo poorly laid, that the moſt ſhort-ſighted might be able to look through with half an Eye; they have expos'd the Weakneſs of their Cauſe to the Contempt of Wiſe men, and its Deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the ſcorn and deteſtation of all others. Theſe things being certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true, as I am able further to prove, if you or any one ſhall make the leaſt doubt of them, I muſt beg pardon of the Reverend Fathers of the Miſſion, if I entertain ſo mean an Opinion of them, as to think that their <hi>Common Senſe</hi> is at laſt vaniſh't, as well as their <hi>Honeſty</hi> and <hi>Learning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By mentioning their Learning, I find I had almoſt forgot that to be one of the weighty reaſons of your Fears; which I cannot but wonder to ſee you lay ſo great a ſtreſs upon at this time of the Day. Time was indeed when we entertained a very Favourable opinion of their Learning, of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59720:4"/> which they, eſpecially the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> have made ſuch <hi>Noiſy Brags</hi> all over <hi>Europe;</hi> a while ago we thought it was in the power of their Elaborate Eloquence to lead Captive ſome ſilly Women; Ay, and that they could by pure dint of Sophiſtry, confound the addle brains of ſome <hi>Crazy-men</hi> too. But now the Good Fathers have by indefatigable Induſtry, and all the ſucceſs imaginable laboured to undeceive the World in this point, and let us, who expected ſuch mighty things from them, know that we were much miſtaken in thinking that they, Poor Men, were in the leaſt guilty of any thing that looks like a Scholar.</p>
            <p>I can't adviſe you, my Friend, to a more infallible Remedy to cure your Ignorance in this point, nor inflict a more ſevere <hi>Pennance</hi> upon you for it, than to deſire you to read ſome of their Writings; and if you are not then fully convinc'd, beyond all contradiction, by undeniable Arguments of their own, that they are as perfectly endued with all the <hi>Dullneſs, Stupidity,</hi> and <hi>Duncery</hi> as is poſſible for <hi>Pedants,</hi> that have receiv'd any tincture of <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> to be, I'll be content to give up the Cauſe. But leſt your Mortification ſhou'd be too great, in toyling your ſelf by turning over that great and nauſeous. Dunghil which the Rabble of their Writers have made; to deal as gently with you as I can, I ſhall (letting alone their moſt Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Preachers,) only recommend to your peruſal a brace of their <hi>Cock Controvertiſts,</hi> and ſuch I'll aſſure you as are <hi>leading men</hi> among the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> too, and when you are become a little acquainted with them, you may eaſily gueſs what the Poor <hi>Under-pullers</hi> are.</p>
            <p>The two mighty <hi>Heroes</hi> I mean, are the Profound <hi>Sabran,</hi> and the Accurate <hi>Pulton.</hi> Now were it poſſible for the Fable to be true, of the Mountains being with Child, lying in, and being brought to Bed of a Mouſe, (O how will the little Curs ſnarl at me here for my Nonſenſe) and I were invited to the Labour as Goſſip, I am ſure the whole Comedy wou'd not force a greater laughter from me, then I find my ſelf inclin'd to, when I ſeriouſly think of theſe men, when I conſider with my ſelf what a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Tools they have here ſent us over from beyond Sea, to perſwade three Nations out of their Senſes.</p>
            <p>When you firſt ſet your eyes upon the Great <hi>Sabran,</hi> you'll find him look ſo big, that Captain <hi>Hackum</hi> himſelf, with his truſs'd up Whiskers, does not carry half the terror in his Countenance: But, alas, when he comes to enter the <hi>Liſts,</hi> you'll ſee his Learned Adverſary Mr. <hi>G.</hi> put him to ſuch miſerable ſhifts, by tracing his Thefts, diſcovering his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries, and Baffling him when he makes but the leaſt offer of an Argument to defend himſelf withal, that even you will pity him; I am ſure I did as far as the great Eſteem and Affection I bear for the whole Party wou'd permit me.</p>
            <p>But yet, not to defraud the <hi>Father</hi> of his due praiſe, I cannot forbear
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59720:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> doing him Juſtice, by taking notice of a very notable <hi>Stratagem</hi> of his. (You may wonder perhaps, after what has been ſaid to hear that any ſuch thing ſhou'd proceed from him) but a Stratagem I do aſſure you it was, and ſuch a one as had it but hit, would have ſmelt not a little of the <hi>Genuin</hi> Spirit of an <hi>Ancient Jeſuit.</hi> When his Antagoniſt, like another <hi>Peleus,</hi> had Maul'd this our <hi>Proteus,</hi> firſt in the form of <hi>Sabran,</hi> then in the likeneſs of <hi>Natalis Alexander,</hi> and batter'd him under the Shapes of ſo many ſuppoſititious <hi>Fathers,</hi> he was reſolv'd at laſt to appear as fierce as a <hi>Lion,</hi> (a <hi>Smithfield</hi> one) and up ſtarts he in the figure of a <hi>Non-Con-Parſon,</hi> and falls a bleating moſt terribly at his Adverſary. But that Jilting Baggage <hi>Fortune,</hi> which loves to thwart all <hi>Wiſe</hi> undertakings, brought our <hi>Sly Man</hi> under the ſame Misfortune as ſhe did a more ſubtil <hi>Animal</hi> of the <hi>ſame ſpecies,</hi> who had cloathed himſelf with the <hi>Lions Skin,</hi> and was diſcover'd by <hi>his long ears.</hi> For to confeſs the truth, he manag'd the <hi>Intrigue</hi> ſo clumſily, that the ſubtil Mr. <hi>G.</hi> preſently ſpies out the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>borrow'd Cloak,</hi> ſtrips him of his <hi>Diſguiſe,</hi> and expoſes him to the laughter of all men.</p>
            <p>But now to help a poor <hi>lame Dog</hi> over the Stile, and wipe off the ſcandal that might be caſt upon the <hi>Holy Church,</hi> out comes another <hi>Reverend Father</hi> of the <hi>Society;</hi> who with Hands and Eyes, as it were, lifted up to Heaven, ſolemnly declares that they never have been tampering with Diſſenters, never appear in Jumps and little Bands, but abhor, renounce, and deteſt, all manner of Diſſimulation and Diſguiſements, in what ever concerns Religion.</p>
            <p>But to ſay nothing of the R. Dr. <hi>Sh.</hi> whom I will not diſhonor by bringing him into competition with this Varlet, I muſt beg Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s pardon for keeping him in ſuch bad company all this while: What ſhall we do then for one to match this our <hi>Dreadful Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion?</hi> Truly we ſhall be at a great loſs, for the <hi>Footman</hi> has ſo often <hi>foil'd, tript him up, and laid him on his Back,</hi> that henceforward, even <hi>Porters</hi> and <hi>Cobblers</hi> will think it a Diſgrace to be put into the <hi>Ring</hi> againſt him.</p>
            <p>But tho' the Unfortunate <hi>Sabran</hi> has been thus ſtript of his Learning, Politicks, and Common Senſe; yet his <hi>Philoſophy</hi> will never forſake him; there's none, I'm ſure, that can deny him to be perfectly endued but more eſpecially about the <hi>Forehead</hi>) with all the <hi>Apathy</hi> of a moſt accompliſh'd <hi>Stoick;</hi> for notwithſtanding all his Diſgraces, he has ſtill the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to live, and in <hi>England</hi> too, the Scene of his Follies.</p>
            <p>The Judicious Mr. <hi>Pulton,</hi> may perhaps take it ill that I have been ſo long a coming to him, but it is very probable that I ſhall ſome other time take an occaſion of ſtaying with him a little longer than he deſires. I am a little out of breath at preſent, and therefore ſhall only tell him that I have read ſome of his Works, with as little prejudice as it is poſſible for one to entertain, that has the leaſt knowledge of Popery; and all the puniſhment I would deſire ſhould be inflicted on the overgrown Grammarian, for all the Nonſenſical Ribaldry wherewith he has peſter'd the World, is, That he were put a little while under old <hi>Busbys</hi> laſh, he would then find, that did he uſe no better Arguments in a <hi>Declamation,</hi> than he does for his <hi>Religion,</hi> he'd receive more ſtripes then <hi>Choerilus,</hi> for betraying his Cauſe.</p>
            <p>But to conclude, Sir, I doubt not but that by this time you perceive how deſpicable a thing this once <hi>ſo terrible</hi> a <hi>Bugbear</hi> is, you ſee what ſmall reaſon we have to be afraid, where no occaſion of Fear is; If that party ever had any advantage over us, it proceeded from our own timerous Apprehenſions of them. But they have now been ſo kind as to let us know that all their Plots and Contrivances againſt us, ought to be ſo little the objects of our <hi>Dread</hi> that they are beneath even our <hi>Contempt</hi> and <hi>Scorn.</hi> Our ſafety, as it is inſeparable from that of the <hi>C.</hi> of <hi>E.</hi> ſo it is now together with it eſtabliſht upon ſo <hi>ſolid</hi> a <hi>Baſis,</hi> that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for all the <hi>Southern</hi> blaſts to ſhake it. His <hi>Majeſty</hi> has at laſt ſo effectually ſecured us in the enjoyment of our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> by reſtoring to the <hi>Church</hi> ſuch <hi>Prelats</hi> as are Infer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our to none of thoſe of the <hi>Primitive</hi> times, to the State, ſuch of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> whoſe <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> are Proof againſt the ſtrongeſt <hi>Temptations.</hi> Let us not therefore ſhow our ſelves unworthy of ſuch Great Favours from our <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Injurious</hi> to thoſe <hi>Worthy Perſons,</hi> to whom he has entruſted our Welfare, by continuing to entertain our Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Suſpicions. We have now nothing to Fear, but the Diſmal Effects of Popular Fears. Let us therefore endeavour as much as in us lyes, to Allay them, leſt we run our ſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to greater Dangers than thoſe we ſeem to Apprehend.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>I am Yours, T. D.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59720:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
